Leonard C. Harber papers
Columbia University Medical Center
Leonard C. Harber papers
1926 - 2011
Personal papers of Leonard Coleman Harbor, professor of dermatology at New York University and Columbia University, and served as chair of the Department of Dermatology in the College of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University.
5.5 cubic feet (7 boxes)
Harber, Leonard C.
Augustus C. Long Health Sciences Library 701 W. 168th Street HHSC LL1-111 New York, NY 10032 Archives & Special Collections
M-0086
Arranged into five series: I. Subjects; II. Certificates; III. Photographs; IV. Artifacts and Plaques; V. Writings.
Gift of the Harber Family, 2017 (accession #2017.014).
Open for Research.
Born on June 22, 1927 in New York City, he grew up in Long Beach, New York. Harber attended boarding school at Riverside Military Academy in Gainesville, Georgia (1942-1944) and received an AB degree from Johns Hopkins University (1949). He served in the U.S. Coast Guard (June 20, 1945-June 4, 1946) before attending New York University’s School of Medicine from which he received the MD (1953) and MS (1956, 1959) degrees. He served his internship (1953-1954) at Bellevue Hospital and joined the faculty at the NYU School of Medicine (1958-1973). Harber was also a Fulbright Scholar at the Finsen Institute in Copenhagen (1956-1957).
Harber was first appointed at Columbia University in 1973 as Professor of Dermatology and served as Chairman of the Department until June 1989 and concurrently served as Director of Dermatology Service at Presbyterian Hospital until April 1987. He was appointed Richard and Mildred Rhodebeck Professor of Dermatology June 6, 1983 and Professor Emeritus of Dermatology and Professor Emeritus of Public Health on July 1, 1994.
He died October 19 2014 at the age of 87.
References:
Harber, Leonard, Inactive faculty records collection, NYU School of Medicine, The Lillian and Clarence de la Chapelle Medical Archives.
Harber, Roslyn, et al. “LEONARD HARBER's Obituary on New York Times.” Legacy.com, www.legacy.com/obituaries/nytimes/obituary.aspx?n=leonard-harber&pid=172864061
New York University Medical Quarterly (Summer 1968) v. 24, n.1, page 13.
Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center; Harber, Leonard C.; Dermatology; Columbia University. Department of Dermatology; Presbyterian Hospital (New York, N.Y.); Psoriasis; Skin--Diseases
The papers document Harber’s education and career in dermatology, the bulk dates 1952 to 2011. They consist of correspondence, photographs and slides, reprints and other publications authored by Harber or about him; along with awards and certificates, diplomas, artifacts and plaques.
- Subjects, 1926 - 1996
  Correspondence written by Haber while a student at Riverside Military Academy, Johns Hopkins University, and during his Fulbright Fellowship in Denmark. Includes some letters and school records for his brother, Bennett. In addition, a variety of material such as photographs, letters, certificates, and announcements from his adult life are found in a non-bound scrapbook. The scrapbook includes reproductions of 1926 Columbia University dermatology documents, regarding the dropping of “syphilology” from the department name.
  - Correspondence: Riverside Military Academy, 1942 - 1944 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Correspondence: Riverside Military Academy, 1944 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Correspondence: Johns Hopkins, circa 1944-1949 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Correspondence: Denmark, 1956 - 1957 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Correspondence, 1958 - 1985 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Dionysius Council of Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center programs, 1982 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Fulbright Fellowship, Denmark, 1956 - 1958 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Grant: "Photosensitivity: Environmental and other Factors," NIH, 1976 - 1982 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - Harber, Bennett: student records and letter, 1945 - 1950 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - History of dermatology at Columbia‐Presbyterian Medical Center, 1996 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Personal address book, circa 1953-1960s (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Professional contacts, 1980s-2011 (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Scrapbook, 1926 - 1998 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Selective Service notice, 1952 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Travel documents, 1962 (Box-folder 2.4)
- Certificates, 1944 - 2001
  Includes acknowledgements, medical licenses, society memberships, diplomas, and awards spanning his adult life.
  - Certificates and awards, 1944 - 2001 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - Certificates and diplomas, 1954 - 1963 (Box 4)
  - Columbia University Faculty of Medicine acknowledgments, 1994 (Box 7, Box-folder MC 2-19)
  - Diploma: BA, Johns Hopkins University, 1949 (Box 4)
  - Diploma: MD, New York University, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Carl Truman Nelson Professorship acknowledgment, 1985 (Box 4)
- Photographs, 1953 - 2004
  Includes black-and-white and color photographic prints, the bulk depicting Harber in the laboratory or hospital. Conference materials including a program and paper in addition to photographic prints and 35mm slides. Other slides document travels in Europe, possibly during his fellowship in Denmark. The bulk of the slides are labeled “psoriasis” (1985). Some slides appear in Harber and Bickers’s Photosensitivity Diseases: Principles of Diagnosis and Treatment (1981).
  - [2 rolled oversized black‐and‐white photographs], 1950s-1980s (Box 5)
  - Annual staff dinner, Department of Dermatology and Syphilology, New York University ‐ Bellevue Medical Center, May 20, 1958. Black‐and‐white group portrait, rolled (Box 5)
  - Conferences, 1971, 1982 (Box-folder 3.1)
  - Dermatology color slides, circa 1971-1985 (Box-folder 3.2)
  - Dermatology color slides, circa 1974‐1977 (Box-folder 3.3)
  - Dermatology "#8" color slides, circa 1977-1985 (Box-folder 3.4)
  - International Conference on Cutaneous Aging." Clinical Aspects of cutaneous pigmentation and UV rays," paper and slides, June 8, 1985 (Box-folder 3.5)
  - Japanese Cosmetic Society, talk "#1" slides, circa 1984 (Box-folder 3.6)
  - Leonard Harber and others (black‐and‐white), circa 1953‐1994 (Box-folder 3.7)
  - Leonard Harber and others (black‐and‐white), circa 1960s‐1970s (Box 4)
  - Leonard Harber and others (color), circa 1992‐2004 (Box-folder 3.8)
  - Psoriasis color slides, circa 1973‐1979 (Box-folder 3.9)
  - Travel in England, Denmark, Austria, and others: color slides, 1950s‐1960s? (Box-folder 3.10)
- Artifacts and plaques, 1949-1985
  Includes a variety of materials, such as a felt emblem from Johns Hopkins, his “University Hospital” name tag, and awards in the form of a silver dish from the New York University School of Medicine Alumni Association (1987) and a brick from the demolished Maxwell Hall presented by Presbyterian Hospital (1985), along with several wooden plaques.
  - Johns Hopkins felt emblem, circa 1949 (Box 6)
  - Metal square: Recognition for International Conference on Photosensitization and Photoprotection held in commemoration of the centennial of Shiseido Co., Ltd., November 10, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Silver‐like dish “New York University School of Medicine Alumni Association, The Solomon A. Berson Medical Alumni Achievement Award, May 9, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Presbyterian Hospital award, July 27, 1985; (Brick taken from Anna C. Maxwell Hall) (Box 6)
  - Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons paperweight, undated (Box 6)
  - “University Hospital Leonard Harber M.D.” name tag, undated (Box 6)
  - Plaques, 1950s-1989 (Box 2, Box 4, Box 7)
- Writings, 1954 - 1999
  Consists of magazines, press clippings, medical journals, reprints, monographs, and other printed material authored by or collected by Harber. Of note are three copies of the 1981 and 1989 editions of book, Photosensitivity Diseases, along with the 1984 Japanese translation.
  - Publications and printed matter about Harber, 1960s‐1990 (Box-folder 2.6, Box 4)
  - Reprints authored by Harber, 1954 - 1981 (Box 2.7)
  - Publications and printed matter collected by Harber, 1960s‐1999 (Box-folder 2.8)
  - Book: Harber, Leonard C, and David R. Bickers. Photosensitivity Diseases: Principles of Diagnosis and Treatment. Philadelphia: Saunders, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Book: Harber, Leonard C, and David R. Bickers. Photosensitivity Diseases: Principles of Diagnosis and Treatment. Toronto: B.C. Decker, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Book: Harber, Leonard C, David R. Bickers, and Takeshi Horio. Nikkō Kabinsei Shikkan, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Book: International Conference on Photosensitization and Photoprotection, Kobori, T., Seiji, M., Yasuda, T., & Shiseidō (Tokyo, Japan). (1973). Hikari to hifu: Ko‐kabin to ko‐bogyo. [Proceedings, edited by Makoto Seiji, et al. Supervisory editors: Tatsuji Kobori and Toshiaki Yasuda]. Tokyo: Kanehara [Showa 48 nen (Box 5)
  - Book: Marzulli, Francis N, and Howard I. Maibach. Dermatotoxicology. Washington: Hemisphere, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Book: Fitzpatrick, Thomas B. Dermatology in General Medicine. New York: McGraw‐Hill, 1993; Volume 2 only. (Box 5)